Guide to the Nina Berberova Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1924-1993; Series I; 11.0' (22 boxes)
  - Uzdina, Maia, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 593)
  - "V" general, 1989-91, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 594)
  - Vainshtein, Lia, 1986-89 (Box 21, Folder 595)
  - Vainshtein, Mikhail, 1980-82, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 596)
  - Valk, Gabriel, 1985-88 (Box 21, Folder 597)
  - Vanity Fair, 1991 (Box 21, Folder 598)
  - Vanni, Jacques Di, 1987-88 (Box 21, Folder 599)
  - Vasil'chikov, Georgii Illarionovich, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 600)
  - Veidle, Vladimir Vasil'evich, 1958-74, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 601)
  - Velichkovskaia, Tamara Antonovna, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 602)
  - Vinaver, Tania, 1989 Jul 3 (Box 21, Folder 603)
  - Vinokurova, Irina Evgen'evna, 1988-89 (Box 21, Folder 604)
  - Vintage Books, 1992 Mar 23 (Box 21, Folder 605)
  - Virago Press, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 606)
  - Vishniak, Mark, 1932-65 (Box 21, Folder 607)
  - Vladimir Nabokov Society, 1981 (Box 21, Folder 608)
  - Vodoz, Tatiana, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 609)
  - Voice of America, 1985 (Box 21, Folder 610)
  - Volokhova, Nina Aleksandrovna, 1988-89 (Box 21, Folder 611)
  - Vol'skaia, Valentina, 1964-64 (Box 21, Folder 612)
  - Vol'skii, Nikolai Vladislavovich, 1950-60, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 613-614)
  - Voprosy literatury, 1989-92 (Box 21, Folder 615)
  - Voznesenskii, Andrei, 1988, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 616)
  - Vozrozhdenie, 1958 Dec 25 (Box 21, Folder 617)
  - Vsesoiuznoe agentstvo po avtorskim pravam (VAPP), 1988-90 (Box 21, Folder 618)
  - Vstrechi, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 619)
  - "W" general, 1989-91 (Box 22, Folder 620)
  - W. W. Norton & Company, 1992 (Box 22, Folder 621)
  - Walker, Barbara, 1991-92 (Box 22, Folder 622)
  - Washington Post, 1987 (Box 22, Folder 623)
  - Weil, Irwin, 1966-90 (Box 22, Folder 624)
  - Welleck, Rene, 1964-81, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 625)
  - Wenger, Birgitte, 1989-92 (Box 22, Folder 626)
  - White, Edmund, 1975 (Box 22, Folder 627)
  - Whitfield, Frank, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 628)
  - Who's Who in America, 1973 (Box 22, Folder 629)
  - Williams, Ariadna, 1957-58 (Box 22, Folder 630)
  - Williams, Robert C., 1970-72, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 631)
  - Wilson, Craig A., 1980-82 (Box 22, Folder 632)
  - Wilson, Edmund, 1959 Apr 4 (Box 22, Folder 633)
  - Winckelmuller, Catherine, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 634)
  - Wolfe, Bertram, 1973 (Box 22, Folder 635)
  - "Y" general, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 636)
  - Yaddo, 1964-70 (Box 22, Folder 637)
  - Yakobson, Helen, 1964-80, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 638)
  - Yale Review, 1991-92, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 639)
  - Yale University, 1975-92 (Box 22, Folder 640)
  - Yarmolinsky, Avrahm, 1960-61 (Box 22, Folder 641)
  - Yedlin, Tova, 1981-82 (Box 22, Folder 642)
  - Yevtushenko, Yevgeny, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 643)
  - Young, Kenneth, 1979 (Box 22, Folder 644)
  - "Z" general, 1989, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 645)
  - Zaitsev, Boris Zaitsev, Vera, 1929-68, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 646-648)
  - Zara, Louis, 1969-91 (Box 22, Folder 649)
  - Zilberstein, Il'ia Samoilovich, 1983 May 3 (Box 22, Folder 650)
  - Zimina, S.S., 1978 Feb 6 (Box 22, Folder 651)
  - Zlobin, Valdimir, 1952-57 (Box 22, Folder 652)
  - Zorin, Andrei, 1988-90, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 653)
  - Zundelevich, Avagail, 1979
    See: Lazar' Fleishman, Box 8, folder 183
  - Zvezda, 1989, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 654)
  - Graduate students, 1963-79 (Box 22, Folder 655-656)
  - Unidentified, 1924-92, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 657)
- Writings, 1922-1993; Series II; 10.84' (24 boxes)
  Series II, Writings, is organized into twelve subseries: Books, Novels, Stories, Poetry, Plays, Articles, Book Reviews, Prefaces and Notes to Books, Translations, Lectures, Course Plans, and Writings by Others About Berberova's Life and Works. Projected works are within square brackets.
  A typescript of the Russian language version of Berberova's autobiography Kursiv Moi (box 76) and course plans on the history of Russian literary criticism (box 77) were appended to the collection in 2007. Therefore the box and folder numbering for this material is discontiguous.
  - BOOKS
    - Alexandre Blok et son temps
      - Reviews, 1947 (Box 23, Folder 658)
      - Contract for publication by Actes Sud, 1989 May (Box 23, Folder 659)
      - Corrections for publication by Actes Sud (Box 23, Folder 660)
      - Advertisement, 1991 Oct (Box 23, Folder 660a)
      - Reviews of publication by Actes Sud, 1991-92 (Box 23, Folder 661)
    - [Anthologie personnelle]
      - Contract, 1989 (Box 23, Folder 662)
    - Borodin
      First published edition. Published: Berlin: Petropolis, 1938.
      - Annotated published version, 1937 (Box 23, Folder 663)
      - Copy of Alexandre Benois' note to Berberova about chapter five, 1937 (Box 23, Folder 664)
      - Review, 1938 (Box 23, Folder 665)
      - Borodine (French ed.)
        Published: Arles: Actes Sud, 1989.
        - Contract for publication by Actes Sud, 1988 Oct (Box 23, Folder 666)
        - French translation, photocopy, 1989 (Box 23, Folder 667)
        - Notes for French translation, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 668)
        - Reviews, 1989-90 (Box 23, Folder 669)
    - [Correspondence Alexandre Kerenski-Nina Berberova]
      - Contract, 1989 (Box 23, Folder 670)
    - [Ensemble de trois essais...]
      Full title: "Ensemble de trois essais portant sur Tolstoi, Nabokov et le symbolisme des réalistes russes au XIXème siècle". Anthology of articles originally published separately.
      - Contract, 1989 (Box 23, Folder 671)
    - The Italics Are Mine
      First published version of the autobiography. Published: New York: Harcourt, Brace & World, 1969.
      - Uncorrected proofs, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 672-673)
      - Corrections, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 674)
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 675-676)
      - Reviews, 1969-92 (Box 23, Folder 677)
      - C'est moi qui souligne (French ed.)
        - Publisher's contract, 1988 Jan (Box 24, Folder 678)
        - Preface, typescript, 1989 (Box 24, Folder 679)
        - Corrections for translation, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 680)
        - Notes, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 681)
        - Reviews, 1977-93, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 682-685)
      - Ich komme aus St. Petersburg (German ed.)
        Published: Dusseldorf: Classen, 1990.
        - Reviews, 1990-91 (Box 24, Folder 686)
      - Il corsivo è mio (Italian ed.)
        Published: Milano: Adelphi Edizioni, 1989.
        - Reviews, 1988-89 (Box 25, Folder 687)
      - Kursiv moi (Russian ed.)
        Published: Munich: Fink Verlag, 1972.
        - First draft, 24 pages, typescript, 1961 (Box 25, Folder 688)
        - Early draft, chapters 1-7, typescript, 1960-65 (Box 25, Folder 689-695)
        - Later draft, chapters 1-7 and index, photocopy (Box 26, Folder 696-703)
        - Master copy, chapters 1-7 and "Biograficheskii spravochnik", typescript, corrected (Box 76, Folder 1485-92)
        - Letters from Margarita Sobashnikova and Asya to Andrey Bely, 1925, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 704)
        - Notes on Andrey Bely's diary (Box 27, Folder 705)
        - Notes, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 706-708)
        - Contract with Russica, 1980 (Box 27, Folder 709)
        - Reviews, 1973-89 (Box 27, Folder 710)
    - Liudi i lozhi
      First published version. Published: New York: Russica, 1986.
      - Draft, typescript, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 711-712)
      - Page proofs, photocopy, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 713-714)
      - Corrections, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 715)
      - Contract with Russica, 1984 (Box 27, Folder 716)
      - Publisher's promotions, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 717)
      - Reviews, 1987 (Box 27, Folder 718)
      - Research note cards, n.d.
      - Research notes and clippings, 1984, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 719-722)
      - Les Francs-Maçons russes du XXe siècle (French ed.)
        Published: Montricher: Les Editions Noir sur Blanc, 1990.
        - Chapter one, photocopy, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 723)
        - Corrections, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 724)
        - Reviews, 1986-91 (Box 27, Folder 725)
    - [Materialy 1945-1953: Russkaia emigratsiia v Parizhe]
      - Draft, typescript and holograph, 1982 (Box 28, Folder 726-727)
      - Research notes and clippings, 1986-87, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 728-730)
    - Protsess V. A. Kravchenki
      - Annotated published version, 1949 (Box 28, Folder 731)
      - Annotated clipping from newspaper that printed the snapshot of Berberova at the Kravchenko trial, 1949 (Box 28, Folder 732)
      - Excerpts published in "Literaturnaia gazeta", 1990 (Box 28, Folder 733)
      - Contract for publication by Actes Sud, 1989 Aug (Box 28, Folder 734)
      - Reviews of Actes Sud edition, 1990-91 (Box 28, Folder 735-736)
      - L'Affaire Kravtchenko (French ed.)
      - Published: Arles: Actes Sud, 1990.
        - Poster, n.d.
    - [Recueil de textes dits académiques]
      - Contract, 1990 (Box 29, Folder 737)
    - [Soviet Historians and Commentary]
      - Draft, typescript, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 738-740)
    - Tchaikovsky
      First published: Berlin: Petropolis, 1936.
      - Draft, typescript, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 741)
      - Printed version, photocopy, 1936 (Box 30, Folder 742)
      - Post publication correspondence, 1947-62 (Box 30, Folder 743)
      - Reviews, 1969, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 744)
      - Notes about film based on this book, 1969 (Box 30, Folder 745)
      - Foreword in Russian, typescript, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 746)
      - Contract for French translation published by Actes Sud, 1988 Jan (Box 30, Folder 747)
      - Foreword in French, typescript, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 748)
      - Corrections for French translation, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 749)
      - Reviews of Actes sud edition, 1987-90 (Box 30, Folder 750-751)
      - Tschaikowski (German ed.)
      - Published: Berlin: Gustav Kiepenheuer, 1938.
        - Printed version, photocopy, 1938 (Box 30, Folder 752)
    - Zheleznaia zhenshchina
      First published version. Published: New York: Russica, 1981.
      - Final draft, chapters 1-6, typescript, 1978-80 (Box 31, Folder 753-758)
      - Bibliography, typescript, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 759)
      - Epigraphs, typescript, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 760)
      - Acknowledgments, typescript and holograph (Box 31, Folder 761)
      - Draft of index, typescript (Box 31, Folder 762)
      - Final draft of index, typescript (Box 31, Folder 763)
      - Corrections, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 764-765)
      - Contract with Russica, 1980 (Box 31, Folder 766)
      - Excerpts that were published in news- papers and journals, 1982, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 767)
      - Notes on publishers, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 768)
      - Research Notes and Clippings
        - Maurice Baring, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 769)
        - Moura Budberg, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 770)
        - Moura Budberg and Maxim Gorky (Box 32, Folder 771)
        - Moura Budberg's children, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 772)
        - Moura Budberg's family, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 773)
        - Moura Budberg's translations, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 774)
        - Nikolai Ivanovich Bukharin, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 775)
        - Maxim Gorky, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 776-779)
        - Valentina Khodasevich, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 780)
        - Ivan Pavlovich Ladyzhnikov, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 781)
        - Robin Bruce Lockhart, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 782-783)
        - René Marchand (Box 32, Folder 784)
        - Harold Nicolson, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 785)
        - Boris I. Nikolaevsky, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 786)
        - Zinovyi Peshkov, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 787)
        - Fedor Fedorovich Raskol'nikov, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 788)
        - Sidney Reilly, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 789)
        - Raymond Robbins (Box 32, Folder 790)
        - Richard Ullman, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 791)
        - H. G. Wells, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 792-795)
        - Antiwar congresses, 1932 and 1935 (Box 33, Folder 796)
        - Archival material, 1978, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 797-798)
        - Espionage, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 799)
        - Moscow trials in the 1930s, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 800)
        - Soviet-American relations, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 801)
        - Miscellaneous topics, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 802)
        - Research note cards, n.d.
      - Reviews, 1982-90 (Box 33, Folder 803)
      - Histoire de la baronne Boudberg (French ed.)
      - Published: Arles: Actes Sud, 1988.
        - Contract, 1988 Jan (Box 33, Folder 804)
        - Corrections, 1987-88 (Box 33, Folder 805)
        - Reviews, 1988-89 (Box 33, Folder 806)
      - [Unpublished English ed.]
        - English translation, typescript (incomplete), n.d. (Box 33, Folder 807)
        - Preface, typescript, n.d (Box 33, Folder 808)
        - Preface, 4 drafts, photocopy, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 809)
        - Index (Box 33, Folder 810)
        - Synopsis, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 811)
        - Corrections, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 812-813)
  - NOVELS
    - Bez zakata
      - Reviews, 1938, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 814)
    - Poslednie i pervye
      - Reviews, 1931 (Box 34, Folder 815)
    - Povelitel'nitsa
      - Reviews, 1932 (Box 34, Folder 816)
  - STORIES
    - "Akkompaniatorsha"
      First published in Russian. Appeared in the collection Oblegchenie uchasti, Paris: YMCA Press, 1949
      "L'Accompagnatrice" French editions. Published in Paris by Atelier Alpha Bleue in 1982, and again in Arles by Actes Sud, 1985.
      - Printed version of AAB edition, unbound sheets, 1982
      - Contract for publication by Actes Sud, 1988 (Box 34, Folder 818)
      - Notes for Actes Sud edition, 1988 (Box 34, Folder 819)
      - Reviews of Actes Sud edition, 1985-90, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 820-822)
      - Poster for "L'Accompagnatrice," a French film based on the story, [1992?]
      - Reviews of "L'Accompagnatrice," a French film based on the story, 1992 (Box 34, Folder 823)
      - "The Accompanist" (English ed.) Published: London: Collins, 1987.
        - Reviews, 1987-88 (Box 34, Folder 824)
      - "Die Begleiterin" (German ed.) Published: Dusseldorf: Classen, 1987
        - Reviews, 1987-90 (Box 34, Folder 825)
    - "Biiankurskie prazdniki"
      A number of short stories first published separately in the Russian emigre newspaper, Poslednie novosti, from 1925-1940, that were known col- lectively by the title, "Biiankurskie prazdniki."
      - Original typescript and clippings, 1926-39 (Box 34, Folder 826-828)
      - Annotated typescripts, clippings and offprints, 1926-30 (Box 34, Folder 829)
        Separated as discards by NNB; labeled by NNB "not suitable for publishing"
      - Annotated photocopy of later typescript, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 830-835)
      - Latest typescript, photocopy, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 836-840)
      - Footnotes, 1977 (Box 35, Folder 841)
      - Notes for publication, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 842)
      - Contract with Russica, 1980 (Box 35, Folder 843)
      - "Chroniques de Billancourt" (French ed.)
      - Published: Arles: Actes Sud, 1992
        - Contract for publication by Actes Sud, 1989 (Box 35, Folder 844)
        - Typescript of preface and two stories from the collection (Box 35, Folder 845)
        - Reviews, 1992-93 (Box 35, Folder 846)
    - "Bol'shoi gorod"
      - Printed version, photocopy as published in Novyi zhurnal, #32, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 847)
    - "Chernaia bolezn'"
      First published in Russian, New York: Novyi zhurnal, 1959
      - Printed version, photocopy, 1959 (Box 36, Folder 848)
      - English and French translations of one passage from the story (Box 36, Folder 849)
      - "Le Mal noir" (French ed.)
      - Published: Arles: Actes Sud, 1989.
        - Reviews, 1989-90 (Box 36, Folder 850)
        - Book on tape (produced by Actes Sud), n.d.
          See: Box 56, folder 1275
    - "Florentiinskie bezchinstva"
      - Clipping, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 851)
    - "Istoriia Mashi Mimozovoi"
      - Two offprints, (one inscribed by NNB to her friend, Virginia), 1928 (Box 36, Folder 852)
    - "Iz chego delaetsia son"
      - Printed version, photocopy as published in Vozrozhdenie, #6, 1949 (Box 36, Folder 853)
    - "Lakei i devka"
      - "The Lackey and the Slut," English translation, typescript (Box 36, Folder 854)
      - "Der Lakai und die Hure" (German ed.)
        Published: Dusseldorf: Classen, 1988
        - Reviews, 1988-89 (Box 36, Folder 855)
      - "Le Laquais et la putain" (French ed.)
      - Published: Arles: Actes Sud, 1986
        - Contract for publication, 1988 (Box 36, Folder 856)
        - Reviews, 1986-87 (Box 36, Folder 857)
    - "Mysliashchii trostnik"
      First published in Russian, New York: Novyi zhurnal, #55
      "The Revolt" (English ed.)
      Published: London: Collins, 1989
      - Reviews, 1989
      - "Le Roseau révolté" (French ed.)
      - Published: Arles: Actes Sud, 1988
        - Reviews, 1988 (Box 36, Folder 859)
        - Book on tape (produced by Actes Sud), n.d.
          See: Box 56, folder 1276
    - "O zakoriuchkakh"
      - Clipping of reprint, 1982 (Box 36, Folder 860)
    - "Oblegchenie uchasti"
      - Reviews, 1939 (Box 36, Folder 861)
      - "Alleviare la sorte" (Italian ed.)
      - Published: Milan, Feltrinello, 1989
        - Reviews, 1989 (Box 36, Folder 862)
      - "Astachev à Paris" (French ed.)
      - Published: Arles: Actes Sud, 1988
        - Contract for publication, 1988 (Box 36, Folder 863)
        - Reviews, 1988-89 (Box 36, Folder 864)
      - "Astaschew in Paris (German ed.)
      - Published: Dusseldorf: Classen, 1989
        - Reviews, 1989-90 (Box 36, Folder 865)
      - "Sentence Commuted" (English ed.)
      - Published in The Literary Review, 1985
        - Printed version, photocopy as published in The Literary Review, 1985 (Box 36, Folder 866)
    - Oblegchenie uchasti: shest' povestei
      Published: Paris: YMCA Press, 1949. Collection of six stories: "Akkomp- aniatorsha," "Oblegchenie uchasti," "Rokanval'," Lakei i devka," "Vos- kreshenie Motsarta," and "Plach"
      - Reviews, 1949 (Box 36, Folder 867)
    - "Pamiati Shlimana"
      First published in Russian in Mosty, 1958
      - Two printed versions, photocopy, 1958 (Box 36, Folder 868)
      - "A la mémoire de Schliemann" (French ed.)
      - Published: Arles: Actes Sud, 1991
        - Contract, 1988 (Box 36, Folder 869)
        - Reviews, 1991 (Box 36, Folder 870)
      - "In Memory of Schliemann" (English ed.)
        - Early draft, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 871)
        - Later draft, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 872)
    - "Plach"
      - Clipping, 1941-42 (Box 36, Folder 873)
      - Later typescript and photocopy of one passage from the story (Box 36, Folder 874)
      - "De cape et de larmes" (French ed.)
        - Reviews, 1990 (Box 36, Folder 875)
      - "The Tattered Cloak" (English ed.)
        - Typescript, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 876)
        - Corrections, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 877)
    - Récits de l'exil
      Published: Arles: Actes Sud, 1985 Collection of eight stories
      - Advertisement, 1991 Nov (Box 36, Folder 877a)
    - "La Résurrection de Mozart"
      Published: Arles: Actes Sud, 1988 French ed. of "Voskreshenie Motsarta," first published in Russian. Appeared in the collection Oblegchenie uchasti Paris: YMCA Press, 1949
      - Printed version, photocopy, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 878)
      - Reviews, 1989 (Box 37, Folder 879)
    - "Roquenval"
      Published: Arles: Actes Sud, 1990 French ed. of "Rokanval': istoriia odnogo zamka," first published in Russian. Appeared in the collection Oblegchenie uchasti, Paris: YMCA Press, 1949
      - Contract for publication, 1988 (Box 37, Folder 880)
      - Reviews, 1991 (Box 37, Folder 881)
    - "Strashnyi sud"
      - Clipping and offprint, 1962 (Box 37, Folder 882)
      - Printed version, photocopy, 1962 (Box 37, Folder 883)
      - "Day of Judgment" (English trans.)
        - Typescript, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 884)
    - The Tattered Cloak and Other Stories
      Anthology of English translations of six stories: "The Resurrection of Mozart," "The Waiter and the Slut," "Astashev in Paris," "The Tattered Cloak," "The Black Pestilence," and "In Memory of Schliemann"
      - Reviews, 1991 (Box 37, Folder 885)
    - Three Novels
      Collection of English translations of three stories: "The Resurrection of Mozart," "The Waiter and the Slut," and "Astachev in Paris"
      - Reviews of vol. 1, 1990 (Box 37, Folder 886)
    - "Vozvrashchenie Toni"
      - Annotated clipping, 1927 (Box 37, Folder 887)
    - "Zoia Andreevna"
      - Offprint, 1927 (Box 37, Folder 888)
    - Other Papers Related to Stories
      - Compilation of summaries of French editions of various stories, prepared by NNB, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 889)
      - Contract with Actes Sud for publication of various stories and one novel, 1988 (Box 37, Folder 890)
  - POETRY
    - Berberova's bibliography of her poems, typescript, 1929 (Box 37, Folder 891)
    - "Angliiskii romans," typescript, 1926 (Box 37, Folder 892)
    - "21 noiabria 1958 goda," typescript (Box 37, Folder 893)
    - "Liricheskaia poema," two offprints, 1924-26 (Box 37, Folder 894)
    - "Romashka," holograph, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 895)
    - Stikhi, 1921-1983
      - Early draft, typescript, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 896)
      - Later draft, typescript, 1983 (Box 37, Folder 897)
      - Afterword by Sasha Sumerkin, typescript, 1983 (Box 37, Folder 898)
      - Contract with Russica, 1984 (Box 37, Folder 899)
      - Page proofs, photocopy, 1984 (Box 37, Folder 900)
      - Reviews, 1985-86 (Box 37, Folder 901)
    - Ushkuiniki, journal containing Berberova's first published poem, 1922 (Box 38, Folder 902)
    - "Vechnaia pamiat'," four offprints, 1927 (Box 38, Folder 903)
    - Berberova's English translations of two of her poems, typescript (photocopy), n.d. (Box 38, Folder 904)
    - Various poems, clippings, 1982-89 (Box 38, Folder 905)
    - Reviews, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 906)
  - PLAYS
    Little Girl
    - Typescript, n.d.
    - Malen'kaia devochka (Russian ed.)
      Published in Mosty, #9
      - Reviews, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 908)
    - Madame
      - Holograph, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 909)
      - Reviews, 1938 (Box 38, Folder 910)
    - TSyrk, typescript, 1942 (Box 38, Folder 911)
  - ARTICLES
    - NNB's list of articles she published, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 912)
    - "Angliiskie predki Vladimira Nabokova,"
      - Offprint, 1988 (Box 38, Folder 913)
      - Footnotes, typescript, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 914)
      - Research notes and clippings (Box 38, Folder 915)
    - "Antologiia russkoi poezii," clipping, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 916)
    - "Beria's Correspondence with Foreigners," clipping, 1954 (Box 38, Folder 917)
    - "Bunin i ego sovremenniki," clipping, 1950 (Box 38, Folder 918)
    - "Dva raza takhikh vstrech ne byvaet," clipping, 1940 (Box 38, Folder 919)
    - "25 let smerti A. A. Bloka," photocopy, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 920)
    - "Dve vliublennosti Gogolia," clipping, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 921)
    - "Eight Letters of V. F. Khodasevich to Diatroptov (1916-1926)," typescript, photocopy, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 922)
    - "Istoriia odnoi liubvi," clipping, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 923)
    - "Konets Turgenevskoi biblioteki"
      - Photocopy and clipping, 1961, 1989 (Box 38, Folder 924)
      - "La disparition de la bibliothèque Tourgueniev," contract for French edition, 1989 (Box 38, Folder 925)
      - "The End of the Turgenev Library," English translation, photocopy, 1981 (Box 38, Folder 926)
    - "Liubov' i gibel' Lizy Gertsen," parts 1 and 2, clippings (Box 38, Folder 927)
    - "Looking Back at Tchaikovsky ," printed version, photocopy, 1992 (Box 38, Folder 928)
    - "M. P. Musorgskii," parts 1 and 2, clippings, 1939 (Box 38, Folder 929)
    - "Mekhanism Blednogo ognia ," typescript, photocopy, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 930)
    - "A Memoir and a Comment: The "Circle" of Petersburg"
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 931)
      - Research notes and clippings (Box 38, Folder 932)
    - "Nabokov and his Lolita "
      - Two typescripts (Berberova's English translation of "Nabokov i ego Lolita "), 1959 (Box 38, Folder 933)